<?xml version='1.0'?> 
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY manrevision "1.0"> 
  <!ENTITY date "December 2006"> 
  <!ENTITY appversion "4.4.0"> 
  <!ENTITY app "<application>xfce4-panel</application>">
]>

<article id="xfce4-panel" lang="en">

<!-- Header --> 
<articleinfo>

  <title>Xfce 4 Panel</title>
  
  <copyright>
    <year>2006</year> <holder>Jasper Huijsmans</holder>
  </copyright>

<!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2002</year> <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin
   translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

 -->

<!-- I don't know about this -->
  <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
    <para>
      This document is provided under the terms of the GNU GPL, version
      2 or (at your option) any later version.
    </para>
  </legalnotice>

  <authorgroup>

    <author>
      <firstname>Jasper</firstname> <surname>Huijsmans</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<address><email>jasper@xfce.org</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

<!-- This is appropriate place for other contributors: translators,
maintainers, etc. Commented out by default.

    <othercredit role="translator">
      <firstname>Latin</firstname> <surname>Translator 1</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<orgname>Latin Translation Team</orgname>
	<address><email>translator@gnome.org</email> </address>
      </affiliation> <contrib>Latin translation</contrib>
    </othercredit>
-->

  </authorgroup>

  <!-- 
  <revhistory>
    <revision>
      <revnumber>1.0</revnumber> 
      <date>June 2006</date>
      <authorinitials>jbh</authorinitials>
    </revision>
  </revhistory>
  -->

  <releaseinfo>
    This manual describes &app; version &appversion;. 
    Last updated: &date;
  </releaseinfo>

</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="panel-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>
    The Xfce 4 panel is part of the <ulink url="http://www.xfce.org" 
      type="html">Xfce 4 Desktop Environment</ulink> and features program 
    launchers, panel menus, a clock, a graphical pager and more. Many 
    aspects of the panel can be configured through graphical dialogs. This 
    manual should provide you with all necessary information on how to adjust 
    the panel to your liking.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="panel-getting-started">
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    
    <para>
      The panel will usually be started as part of your Xfce session. For
      convenience, Xfce provides the <application>startxfce4</application> 
      script. The command for the panel is &app;.
    </para>

    <para>
      When you first start the panel you will see a bar appearing at the top
      of the screen and a smaller one at the bottom. Both panels are managed
      by the same &app; program. You can add and remove panels from the 
      <ulink url="#panel-manager">Panel Manager</ulink>.
    </para>

    <figure id="default-top-panel-fig">
      <title>Default Top Panel</title> 
      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/default_top_panel.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject> 
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>The default top panel configuration.</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <figure id="default-bottom-panel-fig">
      <title>Default Bottom Panel</title> 
      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/default_bottom_panel.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject> 
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>The default bottom panel configuration.</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="panel-getting-started-mouse">
    <title>Mouse Actions</title>

    <para>
      The Xfce Panel makes extensive use of left and right mouse buttons. Left
      clicking performs the default action of an item and right-clicking
      brings up a context menu. Ctrl + left click may generally be used as 
      alternative for a right-click. Note that this manual assumes the use of a 
      right-handed mouse configuration. 
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="panel-getting-started-configure">
    <title>Customizing the Panel</title>

    <para>
      Right-clicking on an item will pop up a menu from which you can
      configure the item, move it to a new location, or remove it from the
      panel. The menu also allows you to configure the panel(s) or add new 
      items.
    </para>

    <figure id="item-popup-fig">
      <title>Item Popup Menu</title> 
      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/item_popup.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject> 
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Popup menu of a launcher item.</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="panel-getting-started-items">
  <title>Panel Items</title>
  
  <para>
    The Xfce 4 panel has the possibility to load external plugins as well
    as builtin ones. In this section we will only describe panel items that 
    are installed with the panel.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="launcher-item-dialog">
    <title>Add New Items</title>

    <para>
      When you choose the 'Add Items' option from the right-click mouse menu of
      a panel item, a dialog is opened showing all available panel items. Some
      items can appear only once on the panel, e.g. the system tray, and they
      will appear greyed out when another instance is already present. A search 
      box allows you to type a filter term to limit the number of choices in 
      the list.
    </para>
  
    <figure id="add-item-dialog-fig">
      <title>Add Item Dialog</title> 
      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/add_item_dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject> 
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Dialog with all available panel items.</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="launcher-item">
    <title>Launcher</title>

    <para>The most common panel item is the launcher item. It allows you to
      start programs from the panel. The properties dialog allows you to edit
      or add one or more programs. 
    </para>

    <para>
      The first entry in the list is shown on the panel. When more programs 
      are added they are shown in a menu that can be accessed by clicking the
      small arrow button that will appear next to the main launcher icon.
    </para>

    <para>
      Every item has several options you can edit: name, comment (tooltip),
      icon and command. You can select whether the command should be run in a
      terminal and whether the program supports startup notification. This
      last option allows the window manager to show an hourglass while the 
      program is loading.
    </para>

    <figure id="launcher-fig">
      <title>Launcher Item Properties</title> 
      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/launcher_properties.png" 
		       format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject> 
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Shows properties dialog for a launcher item.</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="other-items">
    <title>Other Items</title>

    <para>
      Besides launchers the panel comes with several other items. We will
      shortly list them here. As always, the best way to find out if they may
      be useful is to try them.
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Xfce Clock</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Simple clock item. You can choose between LED, digital and analog 
            mode.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Graphical Pager</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Shows a miniature view of the workspaces and even allows you to
	    move windows to another workspace by dragging the mini-window in
	    the pager. You can change workspaces by using the mouse scroll
	    wheel when the mouse is over the pager.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Task List</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Shows running applications in a button with icon and application
	    name. Clicking on the button will focus or minimize the
	    application. There's also a right-click menu with more window 
            actions.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Window List</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Shows running applications in a popup menu. Optionally shows
	    active application on the panel.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Icon Box</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A third alternative to show running applications, in this case
	    using a button with only an icon.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>System Tray</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Allows applications to show a so called notification or status
	    icon. This is used for example by some media players and instant
	    messaging clients.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Show Desktop Button</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    When clicked it will show the desktop by minimizing all programs.
	    Clicking again will restore the windows to their previous state.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Action Buttons</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Show one or two small buttons that execute a special system action.
            Two actions are available: quit the session and lock the screen.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Separator</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A separator item shows a line or an empty space between two other
	    items. Can optionally expand to fill all available space; this can
	    be used on a full width panel to have items on both ends of the
	    panel and empty space in between.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="xfce-goodies">
    <title>Xfce Goodies</title>

    <para>
      Many more plugins for the Xfce Panel are available from the
      <ulink url="http://goodies.xfce.org" type="html">Xfce Goodies</ulink>
      project.
    </para>
  </sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="panel-manager">
  <title>Panel Manager</title>

  <para>
    The Panel Manager can be opened from the Xfce Settings Manager or from the 
    right-click menu on one of the panel items.
  </para>

  <figure id="panel-manager-fig">
    <title>Panel Manager</title> 
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="images/panel_manager.png" 
		     format="PNG"/>
	</imageobject> 
	<textobject>
	  <phrase>Panel Manager dialog.</phrase>
	</textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <sect2 id="panel-selector">
    <title>Select Panel</title>

    <para>
      The currently active panel is selected by default or the one that was
      last active if there is no active panel. You can choose another panel
      from the option menu. Next to this menu are two buttons to add a new
      panel or remove the current panel.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="panel-appearance">
    <title>Appearance</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Size</term> 
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Choose the size in pixels for the panel. This is the height
	    for horizontal panels and the width for vertical panels.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry> 
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Transparency</term> 
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If your system and the window manager support it, you can set the
	    transparency level of the panel. You can also choose if you would 
	    like the panel to become fully visible when the mouse moves over
	    it.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry> 
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="panel-position">
    <title>Position</title>

    <para>
      There are two ways to choose the position of a panel: use a fixed
      position or make a panel freely moveable.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Fixed Position</term> 
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A panel can be placed in one of twelve positions on the edge of
	    the screen. You can choose whether the panel should be stretched
	    to fit the entire width or height of the screen. When the autohide
	    option is selected the panel will collapse to a thin line and
	    reappear when the mouse is moved over it.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry> 
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Freely Moveable</term> 
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A freely moveable panel has one or two move handles by which you
	    can drag the panel anywhere on the screen. You can select the
	    orientation and where to put a move handle (on one or both sides
	    of the panel).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry> 
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="panel-monitor">
    <title>Select Monitor</title>

    <para>
      If you use a Xinerama or multihead setup, you can choose on which
      monitor you would like the panel to appear.
    </para>
  </sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="panel-advanced">
  <title>Advanced Configuration</title>

  <sect2 id="panel-config-files">
    <title>Configuration Files</title>
    
    <para>
      Xfce uses the Basedir Specification as defined on 
      <ulink url="http://freedesktop.org">Freedesktop.org</ulink> to locate its
      data and configuration files. This means that file locations will be 
      specified as a path relative to the directories described in the 
      specification.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>${XDG_CONFIG_HOME}</term>
	<listitem>
          <para>
            The first base directory to look for configuration 
	    files. By default this is set to <filename
	      role="directory">~/.config/</filename>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>${XDG_CONFIG_DIRS}</term>
	<listitem>
          <para>
            A list of system directories that contain configuration data. By 
            default the panel will look in <filename 
              role="directory">${sysconfdir}/xdg/</filename> and 
	    <filename role="directory">/etc/xdg/</filename>. The value of
	    ${sysconfdir} depends on how the program was build and will often be
	    <filename role="directory">/etc/</filename> for binary packages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
	<term>&lt;basedir&gt;/xfce4/panel/panels.xml</term>
	<listitem>
          <para>
            This is the location of the xml configuration file that describes 
            the contents of the panel, relative to the base directories metioned 
            above.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
	<term>&lt;basedir&gt;/xfce4/kiosk/kioskrc</term>
	<listitem>
          <para>
            Kiosk Mode configuration file. See <ulink
	      url="#panel-kiosk">below</ulink> for an explanation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>
      None of the configuration files, except <filename>kioskrc</filename>, are 
      designed to be edited by hand; in fact the changes will be overwritten if 
      you edit them while the panel is running.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="panel-data-files">
    <title>Data Files</title>
    
    <para>
      The Xfce Panel will look under the data directories specified by the 
      Basedir Specification for data files, such as panel plugin description
      files.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>${XDG_DATA_HOME}</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The first base directory to look for panel plugin files. By 
	    default this is set to <filename 
	      role="directory">~/.local/share/</filename>.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>${XDG_DATA_DIRS}</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
            A list of system directories that contain data files.  By default 
            this is <filename role="directory">/usr/share</filename> and 
            <filename role="directory">/usr/local/share</filename>.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="panel-kiosk">
    <title>Kiosk Mode</title>

    <para>
      The panel now has support for Kiosk Mode, that will prevent users from 
      making changes to their panel configuration. To use it you have to edit 
      or create the file 
      <filename>${sysconfdir}/xdg/xfce4/kiosk/kioskrc</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The best way to explain the format of this file is by using an example. 
      The xfce4-panel section of your kioskrc might look like this:
    </para>

<programlisting>
[xfce4-panel]
CustomizePanel=%powerusers,foo
</programlisting>

    <para>
      This allows only users in the group powerusers and the user foo to 
      customize their panels.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  
</sect1>
  
<sect1 id="panel-copyright">
  <title>About &app;</title>

  <para>
    The maintainers of &app; are Jasper Huijsmans
    <email>jasper@xfce.org</email> and Nick Schermer
    <email>nick@xfce.org</email>. For more information about Xfce and its
    components, visit the 
    <ulink url="http://www.xfce.org" type="http">Xfce web site</ulink>.
  </para>

  <para>
    To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding this application or this 
    manual, please use the bug tracking system at 
    <ulink url="http://bugzilla.xfce.org/" 
           type="http">http://bugzilla.xfce.org/</ulink>. 
  </para>

  <para>
    If you have questions about the use or installation of this package, please 
    ask on the 
    <ulink url="http://foo-projects.org/mailman/listinfo/xfce"
           type="http">xfce</ulink> mailing list. Development discussion takes
    place on the 
    <ulink url="http://foo-projects.org/mailman/listinfo/xfce4-dev"
           type="http">xfce4-dev</ulink> mailing list.
  </para>
    
  <para>
    &app; is distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License as 
    published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, 
    or (at your option) any later version.
  </para>

  <para>
    You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
    this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 
    59 Temple Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA.
  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
