<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY copyright SYSTEM "copyright.xml">
  <!ENTITY GPL SYSTEM "GPL.xml">
  <!ENTITY appversion "4.0">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "0.1">
  <!ENTITY date "February 2003">
  <!ENTITY app "<application>xfce4-panel</application>">
]>

<article id="index" lang="en">

<!-- Header -->
<articleinfo>

  <title>XFce Panel Manual V&manrevision;</title>       
    
  <copyright>
    <year>2003</year>
    <holder>Jasper Huijsmans</holder>
  </copyright>

<!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2002</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

  -->
  
  <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
    <para>
      This document is provided under the terms of the GNU GPL, version 2 or
      (at your option) any later version.
    </para>
  </legalnotice>

  <authorgroup>

    <author>
      <firstname>Jasper</firstname>
      <surname>Huijsmans</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<address><email>huysmans@users.sourceforge.net</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

<!-- This is appropriate place for other contributors: translators,
     maintainers,  etc. Commented out by default.
     
    <othercredit role="translator">
	      <firstname>Latin</firstname> 
	      <surname>Translator 1</surname> 
	      <affiliation> 
		      <orgname>Latin Translation Team</orgname> 
		      <address> <email>translator@gnome.org</email> </address> 
	      </affiliation>
	      <contrib>Latin translation</contrib>
    </othercredit>
-->
      
  </authorgroup>

  <revhistory>
    <revision>
      <revnumber>&manrevision;</revnumber>
      <date>&date;</date>
      <authorinitials>jbh</authorinitials>
    </revision>
  </revhistory>

  <releaseinfo>This manual describes &app; version &appversion;</releaseinfo>
  
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="panel-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  
  <para>The XFce panel is part of the XFce Desktop Environment and features 
    program lauchers, popup menus, a desktop switcher and more. The actual
    command to run is &app;. Many aspects of the panel can be configured 
    through graphical dialogs.</para>

  <para>XFce is a collection of programs that together provide a 
    full-featured desktop environment. It aims to be fast and lightweight,
    while still being visually appealing and easy to use. The following 
    programs are currently part of XFce:</para>

  <variablelist>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Window Manager (<application>xfwm4</application>)</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>Handles the placement of windows on the screen and provides
	  decorative borders.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Panel (&app;)</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>The program described in this manual.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Desktop Manager (<application>xfdesktop</application>)</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>Sets a background color or image and provides a menu when you 
	  click on the desktop background.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>File Manager (<application>xffm</application>)</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>Fast file manager.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Utilities</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>Several smaller programs and scripts, for instance a taskbar
	  (<application>xftaskbar4</application>) and a run dialog
	  (<application>xfrun4</application>). </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
  </variablelist>

  <para>For more information visit the 
    <ulink url="http://www.xfce.org" type="http">XFce website</ulink>.
  </para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="panel-getting-started">
  <title>Getting Started</title>

  <para>The usual way to run the panel is at the end of your
    <filename>~/.xinitrc</filename> file or <filename>~/.xsession</filename>
    if you use a graphical login manager.</para>

  <para>Here is an example of such a file, also using other components of
    the XFce Desktop Environment:</para>

  <programlisting>
# window manager (go to background after initialization)
xfwm4 --daemon

# taskbar
xftaskbar4 &amp;

# background, menu and other desktop settings
xfdesktop &amp;

# finally, run the panel 
# You can exit your session by choosing exit from the panel
exec xfce4-panel
  </programlisting>

  <para>To find out how to obtain all these programs visit the 
    <ulink url="http://www.xfce.org" type="http">XFce website</ulink>.
  </para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="panel-use">
  <title>Using the XFce Panel</title>

  <para>When you start the panel you will see a bar apearing at the bottom
    of your screen, looking like this:</para>

  <figure id="default-panel-fig">
    <title>Default XFce panel</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/default_panel.png" format="PNG"/>
	</imageobject>
	<!--
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/default_panel.eps" format="EPS"/>
	</imageobject>
	-->
	<textobject>
	  <phrase>Shows XFce panel default configuration. Contains several
	    launchers, a new mail monitor, a clock and a desktop switcher. 
	    Also shows an opened subpanel.</phrase>
	</textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>The figure shows the default panel configuration with one open 
    subpanel and the mouse hovering over the setup button, making it show a 
    tooltip.</para>

  <para>The two strips on either side of the panel are move handles which
    you can use to drag the panel anywhere on the screen. Right clicking (or
    Shift-click) shows a popup menu &mdash; go on, try it ;-)</para>

  <para>The area between the move handles contains panel items. There are
    several types of items, for instance program launchers, a clock and a
    desktop switcher.</para>
  
  <para>Most items perform an action when clicked, like launching a program 
    or switching to another virtual desktop. Right-clicking will open a popup
    menu, from which you can open a dialog to change item properties, remove 
    an item or add a new item to the panel.</para>

  <para>Panel items can have a subpanel associated with it, which can be
    opened by clicking on the button next to the item. Use the right mouse
    button to open a dialog to change the properties of the items on the
    subpanel.</para>

  <para>Panel preferences can be changed from the XFce settings manager, which
    can be started either from the 'Setup' button on the panel (see 
    <xref linkend="default-panel-fig"/>) or from the right-click menu on the 
    move handles.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="panel-prefs">
  <title>Customization</title>

  <sect2 id="settings">
    <title>Panel Preferences</title>

    <para>The properties dialog for the XFce panel can be opened from the
      XFce settings manager, which can be started from the panel using the
      setup button as shown in <xref linkend="default-panel-fig"/> or from 
      the right-click menu on the panel handles. The latter menu also 
      provides direct access to the panel properties dialog.</para>

    <para>Size, orientation, popup position and icon theme.</para>

    <para>Panel layer and centering.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="panel-items">
    <title>Panel Items</title>

    <para>You can add panel items from the right-click menu on another item
      or the move handles. To remove panel items use the right-click menu 
      or the 'Remove' button in the item properties dialog. </para>

    <para>The properties dialog can be opened from the right-click menu on
      the item. Each type of panel item has its own configuration dialog.
      You can also change to another item type in this dialog, e.g. turn a
      launcher icon into a clock or vice versa.</para>

    <para>Launcher, clock, mailcheck, switcher and systembuttons.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="subpanels">
    <title>Subpanels</title>

    <para>Use the 'Add laucher' item at the top of a subpanel to add an item
      to a subpanel or drag an executable to this item from a file manager. 
      To remove items from a subpanel use the 'Remove' button in the item 
      properties dialog. </para>

    <para>The properties dialog for a subpanel item is opened immediately 
      when clicking the right mouse button. The dialog itself is very 
      similar to the dialog for Launcher type panel items.</para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>

&copyright;

&GPL;

</article>
